What is a demon? A supernatural being? A person with unusual drive? Well, yes. But in the
context of UNIX, a demon is a long-running background process that listens for requests
and performs service when needed. It's similar to a ZOS-started task. In Greek mythology,
demons were helpers, hence the name of these processes in UNIX.
ZOS-UNIX has several system demons. iNet-D is the listener program which receives incoming
logins. It now provides support for IPv6. R-Login and O-Telnet-D are the demons started
for each user by iNet-D, depending on the client program used to request the login.
The CRON demon is a time demon. It starts requests at specific times from inputs stored
in specific files. R-E-X-E-C-D is a demon that receives requests from remote clients
for execution of a command under the ZOS-UNIX shell.
As you know by now, there are two categories of ZOS-UNIX shell users that's superuser
and user, and the superuser has special authority to perform certain tasks, such as mounting
and unmounting a file system. The superuser can also access all ZOS-UNIX services and
all files in the hierarchical file system. ZOS-UNIX users have a numerical user identifier.
The superuser has a UID of 0, while all others have UIDs between 1 and 2 billion. ZOS-UNIX
users are ZOS users defined to RACF within an OMVS segment containing their UID, user
identification number, home, the user's initial working directory in the HFS, and
program, the program name path of the shell. These users may or may not have TSOE privileges.
All users should have a unique UID, although multiple users within the same UID are supported.
Superusers should have their own standard UID, and then they can switch into superuser
status when they need to perform authorised functions.
ZOS-UNIX users belong to groups similar to ZOS groups in RACF. The ZOS groups defined
in RACF can be defined as ZOS-UNIX groups by adding a group identifier number or a GID.
The SU shell command allows a user to change the user ID associated with a session. SU starts
a new shell and lets the user operate in it with the privileges of a superuser or another
user. If no user ID is specified on the command, SU changes the user's authorization to that
of the superuser. If a user ID is specified, SU changes the user's authorization to that
specific user's ID. The new environment is built, and then a new session is initiated.
The new session is run as a child shell of the shell issuing the SU command. There are
different methods that can be employed to switch to superuser. Using the SU command
creates a sub-shell, where the user has superuser authority, and authorised commands
can be executed. When the sub-shell session is ended, the user returns to the first shell
session as a regular user. The SU command, along with the bpx.superuser-racf facility
class, allows an installation to define system administrators in RACF with non-zero UIDs.
The superuser concept in standard UNIX is more or less all or nothing in relation to
security and special authority. However, by using the RACF bpx facility classes, you
can better control what users can and cannot do. Also, a RACF UNIX PRIV class exists, making
it possible to establish better granularity for some special authorisations. By defining
profiles in the UNIX PRIV class, you may specifically grant certain superuser privileges with a high
degree of granularity to users who do not have superuser authority. This allows you to minimise
the number of assignments of the superuser authority at your installation, and it reduces
your security risk. So, we've seen something about special privileges and authority related
to different users. In the next video, we'll return to talking about processes.